Hi, בוקר טוב Boker tov everybody. Today's דף daf is דף ו.
daf vav. We pick up at the bottom of ה עמוד ב.
hay amud bet. And we're dealing finally we're done with the opening
אגדתא, aggadata, we're back to the משנה mishna that spoke about the
days that you don't three days you don't do business before their
holidays. And the גמרא Gemara wants to understand why three days? So
of course the irony is that rather than just saying like this
is what it was normally for the pagan, you know, the גמרא
Gemara doesn't really bring in the actual
empirical evidence about how often how big the lead-up would be to
their holiday, the assumption is somehow that we're borrowing from a model
that we're familiar with within the rabbinic discourse. Either, you know, within
for Jews or for בני נח. Bnei Noach. So it says, you
know, make up your mind like for Jews sometimes we have one
day before, sometimes we have 30 days before, whereas the three days,
so it says, well for בני נח Bnei Noach since normally their
sacrifices they don't have to check them so much for blemishes because
it's only a problem if it's missing an entire limb, so three
days suffices. Of course the irony still being that we're assuming that
the current pagans are following the laws of בני נח, Bnei Noach,
which רש"י Rashi sort of acknowledges, you know, because רש"י Rashi says
well what it used to be for בני נח, Bnei Noach, you
know, that's what, you know, is still the vestige of that still
is in terms of the contemporary practice, why take them three days
before. Now the other thing we're going to continue with that in
a minute, but the other thing that's really important to sort of
say at the outset is the focus on sacrifices. And this is
going to be important in a little while, which is why is
it that you don't do business before.
So right now the entire focus on sacrifices makes it sound that
the reason you don't do business before is because somehow it contributes
to their preparing the sacrifices, either they're buying the animals that they
need or other things that are accoutrements for the sacrifices but it
has a very much of a sacrifice type of a focus, which
is one possibility, which I want you to keep in mind. But
the other possibility that רש"י Rashi said way at the beginning on
the משנה, mishna, and that's sort of a more generic possibility is
well because this interaction makes them happy, it's happy that they collected
a debt, it's happy they paid off a debt, it's whatever some
type of a sense of it increases their joy and therefore that's
going to increase their joy on their holiday and increase their, you
know, appreciation in their thanksgivings to their god. So if it's all
about joy, what is the emphasis here on three days in preparing
sacrifices? So תוספות Tosafot says he actually quotes רש"י Rashi although it's
not in our רש"י Rashi that yeah well that the period that
is the period the period that they are leading into in terms
of preparing for their sacrifice, you know, this is the lead-up period
of the holiday. So the sacrifice is not what it's about, you
know, it's because three days they're getting ready for their sacrifice that
makes the three days before, you know, the busy period before the
holiday and that's where any type of interaction that they do they
will translate into seeing it through the lens of the holiday that's
coming up and therefore being grateful and giving thanks on their holiday.
So that's two ways of understanding the focus here on this three
days to prepare the sacrifices. Is it that the whole problem is
supporting them in their sacrifices or is it because of that three
days of sacrifices that creates this as the period that is the
period of lead-up and therefore for all types of business interaction, you
know, it'll lead to gratitude and so on. Okay so that's an
important question in general what this issue is about. Let's pick up
at the bottom of ה עמוד ב. hay amud bet. It says
like this,
so the גמרא Gemara says that בני נח Bnei Noach it's only
an issue of missing a limb on an animal for a sacrifice
דאמר de'amar we'll pick up five lines from the bottom by the
asterisks, דאמר רבי אלעזר מניין למחוסר אבר דאסור לבני נח. de'amar Rabbi
Elazar minayin l'mechusar eivar d'asur livnei Noach. How do you know an
animal missing a limb is a problem for בני נח Bnei Noach
sacrifice? דכתיב ומכל החי מכל בשר שנים מכל. de'ketiv u'mikol hachai mikol
basar shnayim mikol. אמרה תורה הוי בהמה שחיין ראשי איבריה שלו. Amar
Torah havei beheima she'chayin rashei eivareha shelo. So it's by נח Noach
it says, you know from any from all the living things and
the תורה Torah is saying הוי בהמה שחיין ראשי איבריה שלו havei
beheima she'chayin rashei eivareha shelo מכל החי mikol hachai is that
the entire animal is like alive, all of the limbs are alive,
are present. So the גמרא Gemara says והאי לא מיבעי ליה למעוטי
טריפה דלא. v'hai lo miba lei l'm'utei tereifa d'lo. So wait you
can't say that you need that to tell you it's not missing
a limb. You need it to tell you חי chai means that
it has full life, that a to say exclude that an animal
that it has an internal injury is invalid. So the גמרא Gemara
says טריפה מלחיות זרע נפקא. tereifa me'l'hachayot zera nafka. No no no
טריפה tereifa we says because the end of the verse says by
נח Noach bring an animal לחיות זרע l'hachayot zera to bring forth
a seed on the and therefore the assumption is that a טריפה
tereifa that can't live out the year also cannot give birth, this
is a discussion in the גמרא, Gemara, that's the assumption here. Okay
so therefore we already know it's not a טריפה tereifa because it
says it has to be able to give birth. So מכל החי
mikol hachai is coming to tell me that all of the limbs
have to be present. So the גמרא Gemara says הניחא למאן דאמר
טריפה אינה יולדת. hani'cha l'man d'amar tereifa eina yoledet. That's good if
we say that a טריפה tereifa normally does not give birth. So
therefore לחיות זרע l'hachayot zera excludes a טריפה tereifa and מכל החי
mikol hachai tells you that it has to have all the limbs.
אלא למאן דאמר טריפה יולדת Ela l'man d'amar tereifa yoledet but if
you say that a טריפה tereifa does give birth, so מאי איכא
למימר mai ika l'meimar what can you say? Right, so then we
already need מכל החי mi-kol ha-chai to exclude a טריפה treifa before
we get around to the issue of the limbs. So the גמרא
Gemara says
אמר קרא איתך בדומים לך. amar kra itcha bi-domim lach. So it
says
amongst
among you. תביא איתך tavi itcha you should bring with you. It
has to be similar to you, meaning it has to have all
of the limbs. ודילמא u-dilma
or איתך itcha has to be not a טריפה. treifa. So already
from the איתך itcha you know not a טריפה. treifa. So therefore
from the what do you call it, from the מכל החי mi-kol
ha-chai you're going to learn out that it has to have all
of its all all of its limbs present. So now the גמרא
Gemara says ודילמא נח גופיה טריפה הוה. u-dilma Noach gufei treifa havae.
So maybe נח Noach was a טריפה, treifa, so איתך itcha would
not have excluded a טריפה. treifa. No, תמים כתיב. tamim ksiv. It
says that he was whole. תמים tamim is funny. It's the whole
word that's used in contrast to a בעל מום, baal mum, to
a blemish. So the גמרא Gemara says כתיב ביה. ksiv bei. ודילמא
תמים בדרכיו הוה. u-dilma tamim b’drachav havae. Maybe he was perfect in
his ways. צדיק כתיב. tzadik ksiv. No, it also says צדיק. tzadik.
That means that he was righteous. So תמים tamim must mean he
was unblemished. ודילמא תמים בדרכיו וצדיק במעשיו הוה. u-dilma tamim b’drachav v’tzadik
b’maasav havae.
That's a nice distinction. תמים tamim means so what's the difference? צדיק
tzadik means you act in upright ways, but תמים tamim means you
have a perfect character. It's not always the same, your character and
how you act. לא סלקא דעתך. lo salka dach-tich. No, דנח גופיה
טריפה הוה. d’Noach gufei treifa havae. That wouldn't make sense to think
that נח Noach was a טריפה. treifa. דאי סלקא דעתך נח טריפה
הוה, d’ei salka dach-tich Noach treifa havae, if he was a טריפה,
treifa, אמר ליה רחמנא כוותיך אייתי ומשאר לא תייתי. amar lei rachmana
k’vasich aisi u-mish-ar lo taisi.
Why would it say איתך? itcha? It'd have to be like you.
God would דווקא davka want נח Noach to bring in a טריפה?
treifa? It must be the fact that the תורה Torah wants it
to be like נח Noach would only make sense if נח Noach
wasn't a טריפה treifa and the תורה Torah was saying make sure
the animals are also not טריפות. treifos. And then and then מכל
החי mi-kol ha-chai is coming to say it also can't be missing
a limb. Anyway, והא דנפקא ליה מאיתך לחיות למה לי? v’ha d’nafka
lei m’itcha l’chai-yos lama li? If איתך itcha is coming to exclude
a טריפה, treifa, why does the תורה Torah have to say bring
in animals that they can bring forth seed, that they can bear
progeny? So the obvious פשט pshat is because that's what's the point.
Anyway, אי מאיתך, ei m’itcha, because the גמרא Gemara says אי מאיתך
הוה אמינא לצוותא בעלמא. ei m’itcha hava amina l’tzavsa b’alma. And even
זקן zaken and even סריס. saris. Because if we just said איתך,
itcha, we would have said okay, not a טריפה, treifa, but maybe
just Noach needs Noach's going to get bored on the ark for
that long. He doesn't have any TV, no cell surface. So he
needs the animals
for company, for and therefore even if they're old and a eunuch
or whatever, and even if they can't bear progeny. כתב רחמנא זרע.
ksav rachmana zera. So that's why it says no, the point of
this is that the animals should propagate after you bring them along.
So לחיות זרע l’chai-yos zera to tell you the פשט. pshat. איתך
itcha not a טריפה. treifa. And מכל החי mi-kol ha-chai is to
tell you that it has to have all the limbs. Anyway, that
is the end of that little דרש drash that we know בני
נח bnei Noach can't bring an animal that's lacking in a limb.
And therefore that's why they only need three days leading up. So
now the גמרא Gemara continues. איבעיא להו. Iba-ya l’hu. Now we're getting
back to the הלכה halachic discussion relating to the משנה. Mishnah. שלושה
ימים הם ואידיהן או
דילמא הם בלא אידיהן? shlosha yamim heim v’eideihen o dilma heim b’lo
eideihen? When we say three days, does that mean they including the
day itself or דילמא dilma three days before the day
itself? It's a pretty straightforward question. They ואידיהן. v’eideihen. Yeah, but לפני
lifnei and including. Right. Three days before
I'll get to it. But the גמרא Gemara at least wants to
explore that. Maybe three days before means that three days including the
day itself is counted as one of those three days. So Michael
says לפני lifnei is pretty clear, which is pretty much what the
גמרא Gemara is going to say, but we'll get to it. תא
שמע. ta shema. Come and hear. רבי ישמעאל אומר. Rabbi Yishmael omer.
Rabbi Yishmael says, we're going to quote this later, a ברייתא. braisa.
שלושה לפניהם ושלושה אחריהם אסור. shlosha lifneihem u-shlosha achareihem assur. Three days
before and three days after is forbidden. So if the three included
the day itself, so then the גמרא Gemara is going to say
you're counting that day twice. אי סלקא דעתך הם ואידיהן, ei salka
dach-tich heim v’eideihen, if it means three not including the day itself,
so you have three, the day itself, and then three after. So
therefore
רבי ישמעאל יומא דאידהן חשיב ליה מהכא וחשיב ליה מהתם? Rabbi Yishmael
yoma d’ideihen chashiv lei mehacha v’chashiv lei mehatam? He's counting it both
in the beginning and at the end? Because then if you have
the איד eid here, and he says three before, so day one,
day two, and this is day three, that's three before meaning three
inclusive. And then he's saying three after, these are the days that
follow. So three before and three after, if the number includes the
day itself, it's a little crazy. He's counting that day twice. So
the גמרא Gemara says איידי דתנא שלושה לפניהם תנא נמי שלושה אחריהם.
aidi d’tana shlosha lifneihem tana nami shlosha achareihem. You're right. It should
have said three before and two after once that day was counted
in the first number of three. But once it said three before,
it's going to say three after even if it means that effectively
we're counting it twice. תא שמע. ta shema. Come and hear. דאמר
רב תחליפא בר אבדימי אמר שמואל יום אחד לדברי רבי ישמעאל לעולם
אסור. d’amar Rav Tachlifa bar Avdimi amar Shmuel yom echad l’divrei Rabbi
Yishmael l’olam assur. Now, this is a
censored... Okay. What does it mean the first day is always forbidden?
It means the day of the איד. Eid. Somebody would maybe say
Sunday. No, well the original גרסא girsa was נוצרי, Notzri, yep, לדברי
רבי ישמעאל עולם אסור. l'divrei Rabi Yishmael olam asur. A Christian, there
you go, a Christian for Rabbi Yishmael, it's always forbidden to do
business with them. Because since their holiday is Sunday, so three days
before Sunday, and three days after Sunday, and Sunday itself, every single
week is going to be totally forbidden with business, you can never
do business with a Christian. Now this is extremely important for the
following reason: because it is the one גמרא Gemara that states clearly
that the גמרא Gemara considers Christianity to be עבודה
זרה Avodah Zarah in this category. Because or, you know, I don't
know, maybe you could say the גמרא Gemara understands that the problem
is not really עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, it's really a problem of
any other religion. But it doesn't seem to be, like other times
גמרא Gemara speaks about that people would do business on their holiday
with a certain pagan non-Jew and it says well I know that
he doesn't worship עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So, you know, it is
interesting question, would it be forbidden how would the גמרא Gemara feel
about doing business if it wasn't... it says לפני אידיהן של גוים,
lifnei eydeihen shel goyim, the original text is של גוים, shel goyim,
not של עובדי עבודה זרה. shel ovdei Avodah Zarah. But anyway, but
the פשט pshat here is is that these are pagan holidays because
the holidays are considered to be the religions are considered to be
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah religion. So by saying that for Christian, three
days before, three days after, it's all off-limits, is basically implicitly saying
that Christianity is עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, which is certainly the almost
universal assumption of the ראשונים. Rishonim. Although it's interesting, I don't know
any ראשונים Rishonim that directly quote this גמרא, Gemara, they just take
it for granted it was so obvious to them that Christianity fell
into that category. The one exception to the rule is the מאירי.
Meiri. The מאירי Meiri says that Christianity is not עבודה זרה. Avodah
Zarah. So the מאירי Meiri says what do you do with this
גמרא Gemara that says, again, the right גרסא girsa he had, נוצרי
לדברי רבי ישמעאל עולם אסור. Notzri l'divrei Rabi Yishmael olam asur. So
you ready for this? The מאירי Meiri said that the word נוצרי
Notzri meant the people of נבוכדנצר. Nevuchadnezzar. And it did not mean
Christians. And it meant the Babylonians, the people of נבוכדנצר Nevuchadnezzar who
were sun worshipers, and because they were sun worshipers, their holiday was,
anybody? Sunday. So therefore, so it's the same point that the whole
week is forbidden because of the holiday of Sunday, but the מאירי
Meiri claims it was not referring to Christians. It is true that
Christians mostly in the גמרא Gemara are referred to as מינים, Minim,
which is like Jewish heretics. Okay, but again, this is very significant
in terms of that. The other significance, and תוספות Tosafot points this
out, is that like why? Why did we need the גמרא Gemara
to say, you know, לעולם אסור? l'olam asur? We can't do the
math? Three before and holiday and then three after is the whole
week? So תוספות Tosafot says, no, the חידוש chiddush is that even
Sunday counts as a significant enough holiday in the... you could have
said like for us, if you were to say oh, Jewish holidays,
would you have included שבת Shabbos in that? Something that comes every
week? Okay, so that's part of the חידוש chiddush as well. So
this is a hugely important גמרא Gemara in terms of then how
do you deal afterwards with issues about Jews and Christians in terms
of are we categorizing Christianity as עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? But for
the גמרא, Gemara, I will take all the questions in a minute,
let me just finish the point of the גמרא, Gemara, it shows
that obviously three means not including the day itself, it means three
other than the day itself. Give your questions in a minute, let's
just finish the point of the
גמרא. Gemara. ואי סלקא דעתך הן ואידיהן האיכא ארבע וחמשה דשרי. Ve'isalka
da'atach hein ve'eideihen, ha'ika arba vachamesha desharei. But if it's three included
the day itself, right,
then Wednesday and Thursday would be permissible. Right? Three before including the
day itself is Friday, שבת, Shabbos, Sunday. And then three after including
the day itself is Sunday, Monday, Tuesday. Wednesday and Thursday should still
be okay. So clearly three means not including the day itself. So
the גמרא Gemara says אליבא דרבי ישמעאל לא קמיבעיא לי aliba deRabi
Yishmael lo kamiba'ali for Rabbi Yishmael it's clear what three means. דהן
בלא אידיהן, dehein belo eideihen, three means not including the day itself.
כי קמיבעיא לי אליבא דרבנן מאי. Ki kamiba'ali aliba deRabbanan mai. I
want to know according to the Rabbis whether three means including the
day itself. Of course, it's a little bizarre, just because Rabbi Yishmael
says three before and three after, right, he shouldn't... what the word
three means shouldn't change. And once it's clear for Rabbi Yishmael it
means three not including the day and three after not including the
day, presumably it should mean the exact same for the Rabbis, which
is what we will conclude, but the גמרא Gemara is being a
little like stubborn right now and saying prove it to me what
three means according to the Rabbis. Okay, there were questions. But if
the idea was תקרובת, tikrovet, as תוספות Tosafot is explaining, what תקרובת
tikrovet is there on a Sunday or for Christians in general, what
תקרובת? tikrovet? Okay, so we... I... so again, I'm not sure you
might have walked in a little late, although the גמרא Gemara before
mentions the issue about their sacrifices,
it doesn't necessarily mean that the whole problem is supporting sacrifices, it
could mean that because it's a period that is of sacrifice, any
type of business is a problem because it will translate. Now the
question is what type of sacrifices do Christians have? You know, תוספות
Tosafot speaks about, you know, what do you do about a... about
a holiday that... about pagan, let's say they have עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah but they don't have sacrifices. Would you still go by three
days? That's still just the standard time once we define it, right?
As long as it's a problem of going and giving thanks to
their god. But anyway, so you don't... I don't know if you
necessarily need sacrifices if it's just to frame the time beforehand, but
תוספות Tosafot does say that for Christians their sacrifice... he says their
offerings are with their money. But didn't Rabbi יוחנן Yochanan say that
was okay because offerings were with their money? All right,
whatever, I mean
we can't go ahead and...
All right, I'd have to think that about, but that's true. Once
רבנו תם *Rabbeinu Tam* is finding a- he might have said that
maybe it was different at the time of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
I don't know, it's a good question. Once רבנו תם *Rabbeinu Tam*
is finding a way to say you can do it with Christians,
right, and because part of it is by framing that they don't
really have sacrifices and so on, how does he explain רבי ישמעאל
*Rabbi Yishmael*? All right, it's a good question. I'll have to think
about it. Yeah, Charlie. Steinsaltz has a note that the רמב"ם *Rambam*
actually codifies this, except that it got censored, and I looked up
the רמב"ם *Rambam* and it says Canaanites. No, not Canaanites. רמב"ם *Rambam*
says, the רמב"ם *Rambam* says that
Muslims are not עובדי עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah *ovdei avodah zarah*, and
then he says, אבל הנוצרים עובדי עבודה זרה avodah zarah? הן *aval
hanotzrim ovdei avodah zarah hein*. But Christians are worshipers of עבודה זרה
avodah zarah? *avodah zarah*. But in our גרסא *girsa* of the רמב"ם
*Rambam* it says אבל העכו"ם עובדי עבודה זרה avodah zarah הן *aval
ha'akum ovdei avodah zarah hein*, which is like a totality. But the
idolaters are idolaters. So anyway, but yes, this is the way that
the ראשונים Rishonim *Rishonim* rule, that Christianity is עבודה זרה avodah zarah,
*avodah zarah*. תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* as well, he assumes it, and that's
why we mention in the very first תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos*, he has
to deal with the fact that all of these laws weren't kept
in practice. You know, the people were ignoring them in terms of
their business dealings with Christians, and that led to ways of rethinking
exactly how do we categorize Christians and Christianity and so on. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* says like this. Okay, אלא אליבא
דרבנן מאי *ella aliba deRabbanan mai*? So what's הלכה *halacha*? So אמר
amar רבינא תא שמע Tash ma, *Amar Ravina ta shema*, come and
hear, ואלו הן אידיהן *ve'elu hen eydeihen*. The following are their holidays.
This is the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* coming up, של עובדי כוכבים *shel
ovdei kochavim* or של גוים *shel goyim*. The original גרסא *girsa* is
always של גוים *shel goyim*. קלנדא *Kalanda*, Calanda, which is like the
calendar day, okay, which is which is usually either the beginning of
the month or certainly the beginning of the year, of the New
Year. סטרניא *Saturnayas*,
Saturnalia or whatever, which is the day leading from December 17th, eight
days leading through December 24th. Very interesting classic Roman holiday around the
winter solstice, around the winter solstice. Okay, we'll talk about it more
later. Okay, and if the New Year day is already around the
beginning of the year starting January 1st, so you're going to see
exactly as we see that these two holidays are almost back to
back. First you have December 17th through the 24th, leading up to
the winter solstice, then you have this other holiday that's right at
the beginning of the New Year. Okay, וקרטסים *vekartesim*, and קרטסים *Kartesim*,
anyway, we'll deal with exactly what these more about what these are
later. ואמר רבי חנן בר רבא Rava, *Ve'amar Rabbi Chanan bar Rava*,
קלנדא שמונה ימים אחר תקופה *Kalanda shemoneh yamim achar tekufah*. קלנדא *Kalanda*
is eight days after the winter solstice. סטרניא *Saturnayas*, and Saturnalia is
שמונה ימים לפני Lifnei. תקופה *shemoneh yamim lifnei tekufah*, eight days before
the winter solstice. And תוספות Tosfos *Tosfos* says obviously there's a few
gap of some days before it, so they don't run right one,
you know, one right into the next. וסימנך
*Vesimancha*, and they last for eight days I should say. Okay, they're
eight days meaning they also range. Right. Well, תוספות Tosfos *Tosfos* says
there's maybe like two days in gap. It doesn't literally mean the
day before. Okay, so it's eight days leading into, maybe a few
days gap, and then eight days and then the next one is
the next one, you know, eight days for eight days after. וסימנך
*Vesimancha*, and the way to remember it because it's in the reverse
order. First it mentions קלנדא *Kalanda* which is after the solstice,
and then סטרניא *Saturnayas* which is mentioned second, which occurs before the
solstice. So that's like reverse order. So the way to remember that
they're in the reverse chronological order is אחור וקדם צרתני *achor vakedem
tzartani*, after and before You have created me. So first we mention
after and then we mention before. Okay, anyway, but that also probably
is evocative because the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* is going to sort of
speak about how this was a holiday that goes all the way
back to the first human being, how the world was getting dark
and he thought the world was going to come to an end,
and then the days got long. So anyway, this verse being created
by God front and back, right, echoing that these are sort of
holidays that are rooted, you know, maybe in ancient, ancient history. Anyway,
ואי סלקא דעתך *ve'isalka daatach*, here's our point though. הן ואידיהן *hen
ve'eydeihen*. But if the word three, when we say three, means counting
the איד *eid* itself, we're not talking about the days before the
איד *eid*. We're talking about the entire period counting the איד *eid*
that's off-limits. Okay, then if it's an eight-day איד *eid*, you should
have said there are ten days off-limits, right? Because the word three
doesn't just mean three leading into the איד *eid* is forbidden, it
means the entire forbidden period is three days. So if it's an
eight-day איד *eid*, it should say ten days are forbidden. Okay, ואי
סלקא דעתך *ve'isalka daatach*
where were we? הן ואידיהן *hen ve'eydeihen*, עשרה הוי *asara havei*. It
should have said ten days are forbidden. No, תנא כולא קלנדא חד
יומא הוא חשיב לה *tana kula Kalanda chad yoma hu chashiv lah*.
No, it says three because it basically collapses the entire איד *eid*
and counts it as one day. Three means, you know, two days
plus the איד *eid*, however long the איד *eid* is. Again, it's
a very funny way of talking. Three before sounds like three before.
Anyway, fine. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אמר amar רב אשי
תא שמע *Amar Rav Ashi ta shema*, come and hear, לפני Lifnei
אידיהן של עובדי כוכבים שלשה ימים *lifnei eydeihen shel ovdei kochavim shlosha
yamim*. So now it's just going straight to the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*
like Michael says, what let's just read what the words are saying.
Three days before the holidays. Okay, לפני Lifnei *lifnei* or before the
holidays, three days. You know, it says before the holidays, so you
put the holiday aside, then three days. So the three days didn't
include the holidays. ואי סלקא דעתך עם אידיהן, if three means including
the holiday, לישני אידיהן של עובדי כוכבים שלשה ימים. Lishni ideihen shel
ovdei kochavim shlosha yamim. Their three-day holiday is forbidden. That would just
make it clearer, although the holiday's only one day, but it means
a three-day period including the holiday's forbidden. That would have been clearer
if he wouldn't have used the word לפני. Okay. וכי
תימא האי דקתני לפני אידיהן למעוטי לאחר אידיהן. Vee chi teima hai
daktanei lifnei ideihen lemotei la'achar ideihen. No, it said לפני to make
it clear that when if we say a three-day period is forbidden,
you don't know, maybe it's one before the holiday, one after, maybe
it's the holiday and two after. Okay. So therefore, לישני אידם של
עובדי כוכבים ג' ימים לפניהם. Lishni eidam shel ovdei kochavim gimmel yamim
lifneihem. Their holiday is of three days, you know, beginning beforehand is
forbidden. So somehow by starting with the word holiday and having the
word לפני come later, that could have suggested that it's including the
holiday. But if you start by saying beforehand three days, it's clear
we mean that the period before is three days, not including the
holiday. Okay. So אלא שמע מינה הן ולא אידיהן שמע מינה. Ella
shema mina hen velo ideihen shema mina. Okay, it means before and
not including. Fine, that's a good point, which was pretty obvious anyway,
but now the גמרא Gemara is satisfied. Okay. So now we know
three days means three days not including the holiday itself, and the
most important thing we learned from all of that was that Christianity
is considered עבודה זרה avodah zarah, and that Sunday is a significant
enough holiday. תא שמע, come in here. Okay. I'm sorry, איבעיא להו.
Ibaiya lehu. So now they ask the next question. Now this question
gets to the heart of what is the prohibition about. So remember,
before we mentioned the issue about a period leading into when they're
worrying about sacrifices. This discussion too is going to sound very specifically
and concretely sacrifice related. Let's take a look. Okay. איבעיא להו. Ibaiya
lehu. משום הרוחה? Mishum harvacha? Is the reason you can't do business
because of they will have, like it be plenty? You know, if
you're doing business and they've got more funds or they've bought more
objects and they're feeling very overflowing in, like, in the, you know,
in terms of their wealth or in terms of, you know, their
ability to spend their money. או דילמא משום לפני עור לא תתן
מכשל? O dilma mishum lifnei iver lo titein michshol? Or is it
because you are putting a stumbling block because you are providing them
with the objects that they need to worship? Okay. Now, what exactly
is the concern with הרוחה? harvacha? Okay, so hold off a minute,
I'll tell you what רשי Rashi says in a minute. But let's
read the גמרא, Gemara we'll help illustrate this by giving a נפקא
מינה. nafka mina. למאי נפקא מינה? Lemai nafka mina? For what, what
is, you know, that's a very critical phrase in the גמרא. Gemara
Whenever you say is it because of A or B, and any
yeshiva says למאי נפקא מינה? lemai nafka mina? Like what difference does
it make? So למאי, lemai, for what thing that's נפקא מינה, nafka
mina, what comes out of making this distinction? What would be a
relevant, you know, difference by making this distinction? Well, like if they
repaying a loan, there's no הרוחה harvacha there. Okay, so obviously the
question is going to be that a lot of these things don't
seem to be either הרוחה harvacha or לפני עור. lifnei iver. Okay,
but yes, but we'll get to them in a minute. But let's
first focus on this. So למאי נפקא מינה. lemai nafka mina. דאית
ליה בהמה לדידיה. Deis lei behema ledidei. Notice again the emphasis on
animal, again sacrifices. The pagan already has an animal. אי אמרת משום
הרוחה, ee amrat mishum harvacha, if the concern is about like increase,
so הא קא
מרוח ליה, ha ka marvach lei, you're giving him increase, you're giving
him another animal, presumably. אי אמרת משום לפני עור לא
תתן מכשל, ee amrat mishum lifnei iver lo titein michshol, not to
put a stumbling block, הא אית ליה לדידיה. ha is lei ledidei.
So you're not putting a stumbling block, he could do it anyway.
So the assumption is, which the גמרא Gemara is going to reinforce
and clarify in a minute, you only transgress לפני עור lifnei iver
if the person could not have sinned without your help. But if
they could have sinned anyway, you don't transgress לפני עור. lifnei iver.
Okay, and we'll see that. But it sounds like, so what, that
clarifies לפני עור. lifnei iver. Why is it a הרוחה harvacha problem?
It sounds like it's a הרוחה harvacha problem because if I've only
got one animal, could I bring this animal by myself? Sure. But
you now sell me another one, but it's my only sheep. I'm
going to hesitate, maybe I won't bring the animal. You now give
me another sheep, or three sheep, I feel like I've got plenty
of sheep, I'm going to be more ready to sin. So the
way we might phrase it is, it's not לפני עור lifnei iver
but maybe it's like I don't know, מסייע. mesayei'ah. You know, it's
not like he couldn't have done it without you, but you're making
it easier for him to do it. Okay, that's what it sounds
like, and it sounds like with both accounts the concern is that
you're participating or enabling his sacrificing.
And it's all about קרבנות korbanos and it's all about sacrifice. It's
just do we define it very narrowly, that you were an enabler
and you were necessary, or do we find it more broadly that
you made it easier? But either way, it's about him bringing sacrifices,
very consistent with the previous גמרא Gemara with the sacrifice focus. Look
however at רשי. Rashi. What רשי Rashi says משום הרוחה, mishum harvacha,
רשי Rashi says, it's about I don't know, eight lines before the
lines get wide: דרווח, deravach, you make things רווח, ravach, like what's
the word for רווח? ravach? Expansive? No, but it's not just a
profit, is it? To mean good money, to be so happy? No,
I don't just think it's profit, I think it means expansive. How
do they translate the word מרווח marvach in the English? Anybody? Anybody
have the English? I don't know,
but no. I think it means expansive. It doesn't just mean they
made profit.
Okay, דרווח. de'ravach. Artscroll says profit. Profit, well 'cause he's probably following
רש"י. Rashi. I don't know, maybe I'm reading it through my lens.
Anyway, I don't think so, but anyway because if the idea is
that he bought an animal, where did he make profit by buying
an animal? Profit you make by selling things, not by buying things.
Anyway, let's see why רש"י Rashi reads it. I read it that
it's two versions of enabling him to bring sacrifices. One is specifically,
he couldn't have done it without you, and the other is you
made it more expansive for him, you've opened up opportunities. Not that
he couldn't have done it, but you make it easier. Anyway, רש"י
Rashi maybe specifically reading it as profit, although again, that would be
more when he sells something, not when he buys something, says: דרווח
ואזיל ומודה לעבודת כוכבים. de'ravach ve'azil u'modeh le'avodat kochavim.
Profit it says? All right, anyway, דרווח ואזיל ומודה לעבודת כוכבים. de'ravach
ve'azil u'modeh le'avodat kochavim. ובאיסורא משום לא ישמע על פיך. u'v'isura mishum
lo yishama al picha.
So רש"י Rashi says the problem is is that you are if
he's making profits, he's thankful to his god and he gives thanks
to his god. So it's not about a sacrifice, it's about giving
thanks. And then רש"י Rashi has another line. Why do I care
that he's more thankful for his god? Is that an act of
עבודה זרה? avodah zarah Did I enable עבודה זרה? avodah zarah. עבודה
זרה isn't just saying thank you. So רש"י Rashi says you transgress
לא ישמע על פיך. lo yishama al picha. שם אלוהים אחרים לא
תזכירו לא ישמע על פיך. shem elohim acherim lo tazkiru lo yishama
al picha. The name of the other gods should not even be
heard through your agency. So since you are even though it's not
an act of worship, since an act of עבודה זרה, since you
are causing a name of a pagan god to be invoked in
some type of religious context,
and that was because of you, you transgress. So for רש"י, Rashi,
it's basically about a narrow sacrifice focus or a broader the non-Jew
the pagan is thankful and gives thanks to his god, and therefore
you cause the name of the god to be invoked in a
religious context. But again, to me it's not so clear that at
this stage we're up to this idea of giving thanks. I think
it could just be two degrees of what does it mean to
be enabling the sacrifice. Okay, because again if he buys something there's
no profit in him buying, there's a profit in him selling. But
okay, that's the way רש"י Rashi reads it. So now the גמרא
Gemara asks this. וכי אית ליה לעבור משום לפני עיוור לא תיתן
מכשול? v'chi it lei la'avor mishum lifnei iver lo titein michshol? And
are you telling me that if he already
has the object,
you don't transgress about putting a stumbling block? והתניא אמר רבי נתן,
ve'hatanya amar rabbi Natan, it was taught in a ברייתא baraita רבי
נתן rabbi Natan says:
מנין שלא יושיט אדם כוס יין לנזיר? minayin she'lo yoshit adam kos
yayin l'nazir? How do you know you should not hand a נזיר
nazir a glass of wine? ואבר מן החי לפני בני נח? ve'eiver
min hachai lifnei bnei Noach? And here by the way is very
important to our whole assumption that לפני עיוור lifnei iver applies to
non-Jews. And they're not allowed to worship עבודה זרה, they're also not
allowed to eat a limb torn off a living animal. How do
you know you can't do that? לפני נח? lifnei Noach? תלמוד לומר:
talmud lomar: לפני עיוור לא תיתן מכשול. lifnei iver lo titein michshol.
So now how does that so the גמרא Gemara says presumably he
could just get it himself? והכא דאי לא יהיב ליה שקיל איהו.
ve'hacha d'ee lo yahiv lei shakil ihu. He could if you didn't
give it to him he would just take it himself. וקעבר משום
לפני עיוור לא תיתן מכשול. ve'ka'avar mishum lifnei iver lo titein michshol.
And nevertheless you transgress. So you see you transgress even if he
could have done it himself. So what do you mean the נפקא
מינה nafka mina is he already has an animal? Even if he
already has an animal, anything you do to assist him is לפני
עיוור. lifnei iver. So the
גמרא Gemara. says: הכא במאי עסקינן דקאי בתרי עברי נהרא. hacha b'mai
askinan d'ka'ei b'trei avrei nahara. Very important principle of לפני עיוור. lifnei
iver. No, it's only a problem if you're on two sides of
a river and he can't reach over by himself and you're handing
it to him. He stretch one arm and you stretch the other
arm.
דיקא נמי. dayka nami. That also can be inferred by a close
read of the words. דתני de'tani for it says: לא יושיט. lo
yoshit. Do not stretch out a cup of wine. ולא קתני לא
ייתן. ve'lo katani lo yitein. Don't give it to him. שמע מינה.
shma mina. We're talking about a case where he couldn't get it
without you. So that is the only time you transgress לפני עיוור,
lifnei iver, if he could not have gotten it without you. Now
of course there's interesting questions, which we're going to do לפני עיוור
lifnei iver a fun part of עבודה זרה is it deals with
different scenarios of לפני עיוור. lifnei iver. What does it mean he
couldn't have done it without you? Let's say he could have walked
over the bridge and gone to the other side of the river
and so on, right? He couldn't have trivially done it without you.
In this particular transaction he needed your help, you know, but it
doesn't mean that there wouldn't be a way that he could do
it without you. Alright, anyway, these are going to be various types
of issues. The best question is: Can I go ahead and sell
Christian items whatever, that was the context whatever, religion items, can I
sell Hindu objects of worship to Hindus if Michael here is also
in a similar business? So you'll say, what are you talking about?
I'm giving them I'm selling them items they didn't have these items
before, they're doing עבודה זרה. He says: No, they don't need me.
They could have always gone to Michael. So that's why I'm not
transgressing לפני עיוור. lifnei iver. And Michael says: They don't need him!
They could have always gone to Dov! So as long as we're
both doing it, neither of us are transgressing לפני עיוור. lifnei iver.
Anyway, these are questions that ראשונים Rishonim, get into in order to
deal with certain realities of Jews being in the business of religious
items. But anyway, so this is why the גמרא Gemara says that
would be a case it wouldn't be לפני עיוור. lifnei iver. Another
important point that תוספות Tosfos deals with is it sounds like it's
not just that you can't provide in terms of giving an object
to be owned, but you can't do anything that assists. So תוספות
Tosafot says: Let's say... Say the נזיר Nazir asks you to hand
him his own cup of wine, you won't be able to do
it, so then if he couldn't get it himself. So תוספות Tosafot.
then translates this into an important question that he was dealing with,
which was Jewish apostates and, you know, there you are, you're in
I don't know the home of some Jewish apostate and he says,
hey Dov, would you mind taking my lamb chops or you know,
my pork chops out of the fridge for me or something? So
I shouldn't be able to do it even though he already owns
it because of course you could say that's not תרי עברי דנהרא,
trei avrei denahara, he can get it himself. Okay, but still it
would be something I'd have to be alert to. If you look
at the תוספות מנין, Tosfos Minayin, תוספות Tosafot says like this, about
four lines down in the narrow lines, he says: ולפי זה אסור
להושיט למומרים לעבודת כוכבים דבר האסור. Ulefi zeh asur le-hoshit le-mumarim le-avodat
kochavim davar ha-asur.
You can't hand over or מושיט, moshit, again maybe if they couldn't
get it themselves, for an apostate something that's forbidden to be eaten,
אף על פי שהוא שלהם, af al pi she-hu shelahem, even though
it's they own it, כי ידוע
שיאכלוהו והוא נעשה להם כישראל גמור חשבינן ליה, ki yadu'a she-yochlohu ve-hu
na'aseh la-hem ke-Yisrael gamur chashvinan leh, obviously they're a full Jew, okay,
it's out of context but that would be true, ובזה במקום שלא
יוכל ליקח אם לא יושיט לו זה, u-vezeh bimkom she-lo yuchal likach
im lo yoshit lo zeh, only if he couldn't get it himself.
Then תוספות Tosafot then asks another question, let's say Michael here is
my friend and he's a totally פרום frum Jew, and I don't
know he's doing business with non-Jews or whatever, and he says Dov,
would you mind handing over those pork chops? I would be allowed
to give it to Michael because he's obviously not going to eat
it. It's not like you can't, you can only not do it
in a context where there's a presumption that the person is going
to do an עבירה aveirah with it, so then you have to
determine what are those contexts. Okay, so this is the beginning of
a fascinating discussion we're going to have throughout this first פרק perek
about the context of לפני עיוור. lifnei iver. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara
says so that would be a נפקא מינה. nafka mina. If he
already has an animal it's not לפני עיוור, lifnei iver, but there
is a problem of קמרבח. kamarvach. And again is קמרבח kamarvach that
he's making a profit? I don't get exactly the profit you get
when you buy an animal. Anyway, but it's a problem of אזיל
ומודה azil u-modeh that's why רש"י Rashi read קמרבח. kamarvach. Any type
of transaction makes him happy and he's אזיל ומודה. azil u-modeh. So
it's a context of a very specific
sacrifice קרבן korban type of a context or a more general any
type of a transaction that makes him happy. The other way of
reading it is, no both of these approaches are specifically within a
sacrifice, but how narrow is the problem? Only if he doesn't have
it or any way in which you give him more than he
had before. Yes, Charlie. So in those cases it might be possible
to judge favorably, you're going to take the pork chops out of
the freezer to defrost them to feed to his dog, which is
totally permissible. Exactly, so it's all depends on context and what you
can expect. Yes, Michael. Does this with תרי עברי דנהרא, trei avrei
denahara, I imagine it does, you know, well, this apply to Jews
like I invite somebody over I know is going to drive to
me on שבת Shabbat but he'd been driving anyway? Right. So the
question is once it's not תרי עברי דנהרא trei avrei denahara does
it mean it's totally permissible or are there other concerns? You're still
מסייע, mesaye'a, you're מאפשר, mafsher, whatever. So there's like a whole set
of
related concerns which might not be לפני עיוור lifnei iver and might
specifically apply to Jews and not to non-Jews. So yes, thank you
for raising that. It doesn't mean as soon as it's not תרי
עברי דנהרא trei avrei denahara it's totally permissible. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara continues. Okay, so we don't have an answer. We raised
the question: is it because of לפני עיוור lifnei iver or קמרבח?
kamarvach? And we don't have an answer. We will revisit this in
a few minutes. Let's first deal with another issue. איבעיא להו, Iba'ya
lehu, they raised the following question: נשא ונתן מאי? Nasa ve-natan mai?
Let's say בדיעבד bedi'avad you already did business. Are you the Jew
allowed to whatever you did, you bought a TV from them, you
sold them a TV, you took home a hundred dollars, what do
you have to do now with your hundred dollars or with your
TV that you did on the days you weren't supposed to do
business? Do you have to junk it or you're allowed to keep
it בדיעבד? bedi'avad? You mean when they did this purposely, right? Yeah,
you knowingly transgressed. But if it was an אונס... ones... All right
fine, I don't know what an אונס ones is but fine let's
even assume it's במזיד. bemezid. Right, you know you didn't know the
law. All right fine, let's even assume it's knowingly. Okay, נשא ונתן
מאי? Nasa ve-natan mai? רבי יוחנן אמר נשא ונתן אסור, Rebbi Yochanan
amar nasa ve-natan asur, after the fact it's still forbidden. You know,
if not that then maybe people will ignore
it. ריש לקיש אמר נשא ונתן מותר, Resh Lakish amar nasa ve-natan
mutar, after the fact it's permissible. איתיביה רבי יוחנן לריש לקיש, Eitivei
Rebbi Yochanan le-Resh Lakish, Rebbi Yochanan challenged Resh Lakish. אידיהן של עובדי
כוכבים נשא ונתן אסורין. Ideihen shel ovdei kochavim nasa ve-natan asurin. We
have a ברייתא Braisa that says that if you did business it's
forbidden. מאי לאו לפני אידיהן? Mai lav lifnei ideihen? Doesn't it mean
even if you did business prior? לא אידיהן דוקא, Lo ideihen davka,
only on their day of business. So now by the way, that's
important because now what we find out is that ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish and רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan both agree that obviously if you
do business on the day itself it's, you know, any proceeds or
whatever is forbidden. The question is if you actually, how do you
treat the period before? Are we so strict that even the period
before it's forbidden? That's the debate. Okay, איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some
say that the proof started the other way. איתיביה ריש לקיש לרבי
יוחנן. Eitivei Resh Lakish le-Rebbi Yochanan. אידיהן של עובדי כוכבים נשא ונתן
אסורין. Ideihen shel ovdei kochavim nasa ve-natan asurin. The ברייתא Braisa says
on the holiday itself if you did business it's forbidden to achieve
the proceeds. Okay, אידיהן אין לפני אידיהן לא, Ideihen in lifnei ideihen
lo, only on the holiday not before it. So that proves like
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says that before it it's permissible after the
fact. No, the answer is תנא איידי ואיידי אידיהן קרי ליה. Tanna
aidi ve-aidi ideihen kari leh. No, he's not distinguishing between on and
before. It means any of these periods it's forbidden. that the period
before is actually post-facto
okay. בשלושה אסור לשאת ולתת עמהם bi-sheloshah asur laseit ve-latet imahem where
they say you can't do business with them, לא אסרו אלא בדבר
המתקיים lo asru ela be-davar ha-mitkayem that's only if you sell them
something that is durable goods. Okay, אבל דבר שאינו מתקיים לא aval
davar she-eino mitkayem lo but something that's not durable goods it's not
a problem. Now what's the difference? So I would have said that
if you know it's not a significant transaction, if I go to
the supermarket to buy my fruits and veggies, you know, and I'm
a storekeeper, I can sell them fruits and veggies before their holiday,
it's not like oh thank you Zeus for helping me get a
nice tomato, you know, it's like non-durable goods are not significant purchases.
That's what I would have said. רש''י Rashi says a little bit
differently, that if it's not durable then it won't be around on
the holiday itself. So therefore it won't still be there to remind
the pagan of the transaction to be giving the thanks to the
god on that day. I know, so
that's exactly what I'd say for רש''י. Rashi. What, so if you
buy the day before then it is a problem if it's going
to last more than 24 hours, like you know exactly. So I
would not say the question is whether it's going to last till
the holiday. I would say a non-durable good is not a significant
transaction. Okay, but anyway wait hold on. So it says אבל דבר
שאינו מתקיים לא aval davar she-eino mitkayem lo ואפילו בדבר המתקיים ve-afillu
be-davar ha-mitkayem even if it's a durable good נשא ונתן מותר nasa
ve-natan mutar
if you actually did the transaction then you can go ahead and
keep the money afterwards. So ריש לקיש Resh Lakish says ah that
proves to me that there's a period that you're allowed to keep
the money. So that shows that before the holiday after the fact
you're allowed to keep the money. תניא דבי רבי יהושע tanya de-vei
Rabbi Yehoshua דבר שאינו מתקיים מוכרין להם davar she-eino mitkayem mokhrin lahem
you can sell them something that is not durable אבל אין לוקחין
מהם aval ein lokhin meihem but you can't purchase it from them
because the money is durable. So you can't go to their grocery
store and buy their stuff because then you're leaving them with money.
So you can leave them with non-durable goods, you can't leave them
with money. Okay. Now ההוא מינא hahu mina there was a certain
מינא mina okay which is interesting a מין min here right does
it mean a Jewish Christian does it mean some pagan דשדר ליה
דינר קיסרונא de-shadar lei dinar kaisrona that sent a Caesarian דינר dinar
לרבי יהודה נשיאה ביומי דאידו le-Rabbi Yehudah Nesia be-yomei de-eido רבי יהודה
נשיאה Rabbi Yehudah Nesia who was not רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehudah
HaNasi the grandson of רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehudah HaNasi okay and
he sent it to him on his holiday, like they also had
משלוח מנות mishloach manot okay? So part of the ritual of their
holiday was to give gifts to people. So he sent a gift
to רבי יהודה נשיאה Rabbi Yehudah Nesia and he sent this דינר.
dinar. Now הוה יתיב ריש לקיש קמיה hava yativ Resh Lakish kameih
ריש לקיש Resh Lakish was sitting in front of רבי יהודה נשיאה.
Rabbi Yehudah Nesia. אמר Amar, so רבי יהודה נשיאה Rabbi Yehudah Nesia
said היכי אעביד heikhi a'avid what should I do? אשקליה ashklei should
I accept it? אזיל ומודה azil u-modeh he'll go and give thanks
to his god that he gave this gift to this you know
prestigious you know Jew, רבי יהודה נשיאה Rabbi Yehudah Nesia right, the
exilarch and so on, or not
the exilarch, the נשיא, Nasi, anyway,
so so then that'll help support his participation in his holiday. לא
אשקליה lo eshklei should I not accept it? הויא ליה איבה hava
lei eivah he'll have hatred towards me and I represent you know
the Jewish people. אמר ליה ריש לקיש amar lei Resh Lakish
טוב זרוק אותו לבור בפניו tov zerok oto le-vor be-fanav alright, accept
it but then throw it into the pit. So אמר כל שכן
דהויא ליה איבה kol she-ken de-hava lei eivah what do you mean,
he's just taking it and throw it, that's you know what could
be more disparaging than that? לא צריכא דעבדת כמאן דנפל. lo tserikha
de-avadat ke-man de-nafal. No no, I don't mean do it in a
way that looks intentional. Accept it and then after you accept it,
oops! and then it would fall down the drain. So therefore he
won't you know he won't be upset at you, you accepted it,
but he won't be אזיל ומודה azil u-modeh because then he won't
feel like oh look at this, now I've got this חשוב chashuve
Jew who's grateful to me and accepted this gift, because then there
won't be anything relating to be grateful for. Now of course this
is important for a couple of reasons. Number one is is that
it shows that איבה eivah is a factor, which came up a
lot in the ראשונים, that because of considerations of איבה, eivah, you
might be able to you know override or bend some of these
rules. Now תוספות Tosafot says that's not explicit from this גמרא. Gemara.
רבי יהודה נשיאה Rabbi Yehudah Nesia might just have been saying like
I'm afraid of the איבה, eivah, but then it wasn't clear that
איבה eivah would have allowed him to do it, okay? In the
end you know ריש לקיש Resh Lakish basically had a way in
which he didn't just say okay do it because of איבה. eivah.
But anyway it certainly sounds like איבה eivah is a factor. The
other thing though is that now we are completely switching the discourse.
Until this point the whole conversation had been קרבנות, korbanot, לפני עור,
lifnei iver, קמרווח, kamravakh, which I also thought was in the קרבנות
korbanot discussion. Now all of a sudden we're switching it to a
discussion about you know you can't leave them with money, right? It
says you can't sell them durable goods. Durable goods does not sound
like קרבן. korban. Durable goods says you can't sell them anything. You
can't leave them with money and buy stuff from them. And here
explicitly it says the concern is אזיל ומודה. azil u-modeh. So the
concern now is not about sacrifices. The concern is about a more
general thing that they'll just be... be happy and glad that they
made some money or whatever and they'll give thanks and therefore that
could explain why it's not only forbidden for them to receive but
even for them to give because that'll be a source for them
to feel good and to give thanks. Right, so that's תוספות. Tosafot
What does the גמרא Gemara do? The גמרא Gemara frames it as
a problem of לפני עור. Lifnei Iver. Okay, so there's two ways
of reading this. The סוגיא Sugya that on the one hand discuss
קרבן korban and the other about this אזלו מודה. azlu modeh. One
is that these are two separate strands, and the גמרא Gemara basically
completely brackets the לפני עור Lifnei Iver and sides in favor of
קמרווח, karmavach, which רש״י Rashi says is אזלו מודה. azlu modeh. That's
the easiest way of explaining all of it, okay, and therefore, but
then you don't understand the other side. You know, but then completely
the dominant explanation is אזלו מודה. azlu modeh. The other way that
תוספות Tosafot explains it in an ingenious way is תוספות Tosafot divides
the two sets of transactions that are going on here. And תוספות
Tosafot says the following: תוספות Tosafot says that when you do, and
I mean, okay, I don't know if I believe this or not,
but here's how תוספות Tosafot, says. All the other transactions in the
משנה Mishna are one-sided. Either Michael borrows money from me or I
borrow from him. Either he pays up a debt or I pay
up his debt. I give him a gift, he gives me a
gift. Those are all one-sided. Now, sometimes you could say one side
is losing and one side is gaining, but they're all one-sided. The
only transaction that's two-sided is buying and selling. So תוספות Tosafot, says
buying and so if anything is one-sided, you could say that that
makes Michael happy. It makes him happy that he borrowed money from
me because, you know, he got something, he needed the money. It
makes him happy that I borrowed from him cause I'm grateful to
him, right, and that puts him in a certain superior position. It
makes him glad that I gave him a gift, it makes him
glad that he gave me a gift, right? All those things because
they're one-sided you could see how Michael could be happy about it.
But you go to the store and you buy something, okay, what
are you happy about? It was an equal exchange. Of course if
you're the seller you're happy because you made a profit. Okay, but
anyway, but that's what תוספות Tosafot says. That is not such a
basis to be happy. So in the issues of buying and selling,
it's not a general problem of אזלו מודה. azlu modeh. There's no
general אזלו מודה azlu modeh because you did your general business of
buying and selling. The only problem that comes in a buying and
selling transaction is the idea that you're providing them the objects of
their sacrifice. That's why the focus on קרבנות korbanot and the focus
on לפני עור Lifnei Iver is only is in the context of
the buying and selling, we don't have a general prohibition. This is
how תוספות Tosafot manages to navigate why it's allowed to do buying
and selling on Sundays, on their holidays, because he said the general
prohibitions, all types of interactions are forbidden, that's only one-sided interactions are
forbidden, that there's a concern of אזלו מודה. azlu modeh. But buying
and selling, the only real concern is providing the objects of worship.
So the גמרות Gemaras that discuss קרבנות korbanot and that discuss לפני
עור Lifnei Iver whatever, and maybe מרווח marvach might read of a
broader לפני עור, Lifnei Iver, that that's a specific discussion of objects
of worship in buying and selling. The other discussions of אזלו מודה,
azlu modeh, that those are the other transactions. Yes, Charles. Even with
the שיטה shita of תוספות, the only things that would have been
sold for objects of worship in normal circumstances would have been bread
and wine, but the big thing then and now was food to
feast with. And that seems to be not a problem even by
the גמרא. Because you're saying because they're non-durable? Yeah, that's a good
point. Interesting. Yeah, so that's yeah, that's fascinating. I mean, that's a
good question. Like since the whole discussion before came about buying animals
to slaughter and whatever, and here we're allowing non-durable goods, and if
they're buying all this food that they're going to use for their
feast, the implication of the גמרא is that that would be okay.
That's pretty interesting. Anyway, let's continue now, because now what we've done
is, putting what I just said aside about breaking it up into
two categories, the simple sense is that although we raised a narrow
issue of לפני עור, Lifnei Iver, we are now replacing that with
a very generic concern
called אזלו מודה. azlu modeh. They'll go and they'll give thanks to
their god, and that'll have come through your agency, and that'll be
a problem. Yes, David. I'm just a bit confused here about with
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish and just dropping. Does that really sound like
a practical solution? I guess they thought it was. I don't know
what to tell you. Okay, I guess if you do it too
often, it's not practical. Now we're going to go through the different
cases in the משנה Mishna exactly with this issue in mind. Okay,
so let's take a look. להשילן ולישאל מהן, lehashilan ulish'ol mehen, you
can't borrow from them and you can't lend to them. בשלמא bishlama
להשילן, lehashilan, you can't lend them objects דקמרווח dekamvach להו. lehu. Again,
notice this phrase קמרווח. kamvach. You are making things more expansive for
them, or you would say profit. Again, I don't know what a
profit. That's my point, that מרווח marvach does not mean profit. It
means you're making their wealth more expansive. אבל
לישאל מהן, aval lish'ol mehen, to borrow from them, מיעוטא קא ממעיט.
miuta kama me'ite. You see מרווח marvach is the opposite of ממעיט.
mem'ate. Okay, increase versus decrease. That's the what the meaning is. Go
correct Steinsaltz and the Artscroll. Anyway, but to borrow from them, you're
decreasing. Why is it a problem? אמר אביי, amar Abaye, גזירה לישאל
מהן אטו להשילן. gezeira lish'ol mehen atu lehashilan. You're right. The only
reason you're not allowed to borrow is that you'll come to lend
to them, but the real problem is just lending. רבא אמר Rava
amar כולם משום דאזיל ומודי הוא. kulam mishum d'azil u'modei hu. Now
רבא'ס Rava's got a generic answer. No, you make them happy. So
therefore the same way they're happy that they borrowed from you, they're
happy that you were dependent on them and that they lent to
you. So again for אביי Abaye it is much narrower. Maybe it's
not objects of worship, but it's also not some generic you make
them happy. For אביי Abaye it is that you are increasing their
wealth. Okay, some increase, you're providing them increase. And therefore half of
the things of the משנה are not technically a problem. They're only
a problem because of the flip side of the things that really
are the problem. The problems are when you give them stuff. Taking
stuff is only like an extension of the איסור. issur. But for
רבא, Rava. it's a generic issue of you're making them happy. Okay?
Now we're going to continue: ללוותן ולהלוותן, lilvosan u'l'halvosan, to lend them
and to borrow from them. בשלמא להלוותן, bishlama l'halvosan, to lend them
money, משום דקמרווח להו, mishum d'kamravach lehu, you're providing increase. אלא ללוות
מהן, ella lilvos mehen, to borrow from them, אמאי, amai, why is
that a problem? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, גזירה ללוות מהן אטו להלוותן.
gzeira lilvos mehen atu l'halvosan. You're right, borrowing is only a problem
that'll lead to lending. רבא אמר, Rava amar, כולם משום דאזיל ומודי
הוא. kulam mishum d'azil u'modei hu. No, it's all the problem that
they'll you'll make them give thanks. Okay? So there's really three issues
here: לפני עיוור, lifnei iver, very specific and concrete, which is providing
an animal for a sacrifice. Number two, a very generic, all-encompassing umbrella
issue about אזיל ומודי, azil u'modei, רבא. Rava And the narrower version
which is הרווחה, harvacha, which is somehow giving them increase. Okay? And
half of the things in the משנה are really only אסור assur
because of the other half. Okay? It's only really one side that's
really the problem, the other high side is אסור assur just to
round it out. לפרוע מהן ולפרוע להן, lifroa mehen u'lifroa lahen, to
to pay up a debt and to make them pay up a
debt. בשלמא לפרוע להן, bishlama lifroa lahen, to pay up a debt,
משום דקמרווח להו, mishum d'kamravach lehu, you're giving them increase. אלא לפרוע
מהן, ella lilvos mehen, but to make them pay a debt, מיעוטא
קממעיט להו, mi'uta kamami'at lehu, you're causing them a decrease. אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, גזירה לפרוע מהן אטו לפרוע להן. gzeira lifroa mehen atu
lifroa lahen.
No, there's a concern that if you pay up a debt if
you make them pay, then you'll come to then you'll come to
pay up a debt. רבא אמר, Rava amar, כולם משום דאזיל ומודי
הוא. kulam mishum d'azil u'modei hu. It's all because of אזיל ומודי.
azil u'modei. Okay? And therefore, yes, even though they don't like paying
up a debt, in the end they're glad to get you off
their off their back. Okay? וצריכי, u'tzrichi, and you need to tell
me all the cases. דאי תנא לשאת ולתת עמהם, d'ei tanna lases
u'lases imahem, buying and selling, משום דקמרווח להו, mishum d'kamravach lehu, ואזיל
ומודי. v'azil u'modei. That's now here the גמרא conflates מרווח marvach with
אזיל ומודי. azil u'modei. So so it sounds like maybe even אביי
Abaye that more narrowly leads it to מרווח, marvach, and this is
where רש"י Rashi was getting it earlier, it's it's yes, he is
concerned with אזיל ומודי, azil u'modei, but not but only אזיל ומודי
azil u'modei that's a result of increase. The other half is just
a גזירה gzeira and an extension. Okay? So I get doing business
that causes them an increase and they go and give thanks. אבל
ללוות מהן, aval lilvos mehen, דמיעוטא קממעיט להו, d'mi'uta kamami'at lehu,
but borrowing from them that you're causing them a decrease, שפיר דמי,
shapir dami, I might think that's okay. And then that's no, you're
not allowed to borrow you're not allowed to borrow either. Why? Either
a גזירה gzeira or the way רבא Rava would read it is,
forget גזירה, gzeira, there's an element of אזיל ומודי azil u'modei by
there as well, even when they lend you objects, they feel they
feel good about it. Okay? ואי תנא ללוות מהן, v'ei tanna lilvos
mehen, if we just had borrowing, משום דחשיבא ליה מילתא, mishum d'chashiva
leh milta, oh,
he needs to borrow my objects, oh, oh, you know, I'm a
big shot and this this lowly Jew needs to come to me
for my objects. אזיל ומודי, azil u'modei, so there you could have
explained how it would be? I understand, right. If it's like a
rake, maybe not. אבל להלוות להן, aval l'halvos lahen, but to borrow
from them, you know, you don't need to be as dependent to
borrow from them, okay, so there you're being ממעיט mami'at them and
they don't get to be a big shot that you came to
them to borrow money, I don't know, borrowing money certainly gets lets
you to be a big shot. Anyway, צערא באומא אית ליה, tza'ara
b'uma is leh, why is it a pain for them? אמר, תו
לא הדרי זוזי, tu lo hadrei zuzei, maybe never get the money
back. So yes, they get to feel like they're a big shot
that they lent you money, but you know, maybe that won't be
a case that they're happy. תוספות, of course, תוספות says I don't
understand, if you're in the business and charging interest, of course they
will want to do it. Maybe we're talking about without interest. ואי
תנא ללוות מהן, v'ei tanna lilvos mehen, okay, so fine, it's also
forbidden to borrow money, משום דקאמר בעל כרחיה מפרענא. mishum d'ka'amar ba'al
korchei mifrana.
That's because in the end they still feel good, I I'm a
big shot, I lent you money, and number two, I'm not afraid
of whether I won't get the money back, I'll get the police
after him, I got my documentation, I'm going to get my money
back. והשתא מיהת אזיל ומודי, v'hashta mi'at azil u'modei, and therefore they're
still happy. אבל לפרוע מהן, aval lifroa mehen, but to make them
pay up a debt, דתו לא הדרי זוזי, d'tu lo hadrei zuzei,
that money is completely lost to them. Okay? And they're not a
big shot that they paid up a debt to you. So number
one, they're not a big shot, you're not dependent on them, and
number two, that money is permanently lost. So I might think אימא
צערא אית ליה ולא אזיל ומודי, eima tza'ara is leh v'lo azil
u'modei, they wouldn't be giving him thanks. וצריכא, u'tzricha, you need it.
Now all of this seems to be according to רבא Rava's to
say that all of the things are אזיל ומודי, azil u'modei, even
when they they pay up a debt to you and they lend
you things or whatever, it's all an issue of אזיל ומודי. azil
u'modei. It seems to ignore אביי Abaye that says that all of
these things are only a problem because they're a גזירה gzeira about
the other side of the coin. תוספות says, you know, maybe it
could work according to אביי Abaye too. Maybe אביי Abaye does say
fundamentally it's a גזירה, gzeira, but we wouldn't have forbidden it if
there was not some small element of אזיל ומודי. azil u'modei. Okay,
what you get out of this at the end is We move
away from the narrow issue in the גמרא about bringing a קרבן
korban and לפני עור, lifnei iver, you move away from a narrow
aspect of מרווח, marvach, which might be associated to קרבנות korbanot or
might be associated with giving thanks but only when they feel a
sense of increase. And now in the end we're reading it all
through רבא Rava's lens. Okay, אביי Abaye said it's a מרווח marvach
but we allow we forbid them to lend you and whatever the
reverse that's a גזירה. gezeirah. But now we're reading it all through
רבא lens. All of the transactions are a problem not because of
increase, it's not about increase or decrease, it's not about providing the
animal for sacrifice, not providing the animal for sacrifice. It's all a
problem because any of these transactions makes them feel good and it's
all this generic problem of אזיל ומודה. ozil u'modeh. Okay, maybe I
should put this in.